In this American English pronunciation video we're
going to learn how to pronounce the AI as in buy diphthong.
Diphthongs are a combination of two sounds so
they have a starting position and an ending
position. In the first position the jaw is more
dropped than in the second position. The back
of the tongue stretches up a little bit as
the mouth moves into the second position, the
jaw drops less as the front part of the tongue
arches up towards the roof of the mouth for both
the beginning and the end of this diphthong the
tongue tip touches the back of the bottom front
teeth. Let's watch up close and in slow motion
where you can really see the front part of the
tongue arching up. The jaw drops and the front part
of the tongue stays down with the tip touching the
back of the bottom front teeth. Immediately, the
tongue moves into the second position the top
front arching up towards the roof of the mouth. As
the tongue arches up there's less jaw drop here's
the word high. Jaw drops with the front of the
tongue down then the jaw lifts as the front of
the tongue arches towards the roof of the mouth.
In a stressed syllable the I diphthong curves up
then down. High, I. In an unstressed syllable it's
lower and flatter and pitch as well as quicker
and quieter. I, I. The diphthong is unstressed in
the word idea. I. let's take a look at this word.
The jaw drops but just a little bit less than
it would in a stressed syllable. Then the tongue
arches up towards the roof of the mouth before
the tip goes to the roof of the mouth for the D.
The Ai diphthong stressed. Hi, I.
The I diphthong unstressed. Idea
Ai
Example words repeat with me
exercise
wine
bright
guy
allies
sky