In this American English Pronunciation video,
we're going to learn how to make the M consonant sound.
This sound is simply made by pressing the lips together lightly.
Mmm-- while making a sound with the vocal cords.
So this is a voiced consonant. Mmm---
The teeth may begin to part a little in preparation for the next sound.
Mm---
Which will pull the lips a little bit.
Mmm----
Because the soft palate is lowered, air comes up through the nasal passages.
This makes it a nasal consonant.
You can feel the vibration in your nose.
Mmm---
There are only 3 nasal sounds in American English.
Nn---
Ng--
Mmm---
Let's look at this sound up close and in slow motion.
The word 'mom'.
Lips pressed together as the jaw drops a little bit.
Another M at the end.
Lips pressed together. Summer.
Lips pressed together.
The M consonant.
Mom.
Summer.
Example words. Repeat with me.
Make.
Mm--- Make.
My.
Mm--- My.
Forming.
Mm--- forming.
Dim.
Mm--- dim.
Mistake.
Mm-- mistake.
Game.
Mm-- game.
This video is one of 36 in a new series, The Sounds of American English.
Videos in this set will be released here on YouTube twice a month,
first and third Thursdays, in 2016 and 2017.
But the  whole set can be all yours right now.
The real value of these videos is watching them as a set, as a whole,
to give your mind the time to take it all in and get the bigger picture.
Most of the materials you'll find elsewhere just teach the sounds on their own in isolation.
It's a mistake to learn them this way.
We learn the sounds to speak words and sentences, not just sounds.
Move closer to fluency in spoken English.
Buy the video set today!
Visit rachelsenglish.com/sounds
Available as a DVD or digital download.