In this American English pronunciation video
we're going to learn how to make the two th sounds.
These sounds are paired together because they take the same mouth position.
TH is unvoiced meaning only air passes through the mouth TH and TH
is voiced meaning you make a sound with the vocal cords.
The very tip of the tongue comes through the teeth.
The air passes around the tongue. The tongue is
relaxed. There shouldn't be any pressure in
the mouth or a stop quality to this sound.
Just nice and easy.
The tongue has to easily vibrate between the
teeth so keep the tongue soft and relaxed.
The lips don't affect this sound so they can
be transitioning to the next sound. For example
in the thr cluster the lips will round a
little bit for the r as you make the th
Three, three. Be careful with the tongue tip.
Make sure it doesn't come too far forward.
It's just the very tip that should come
between the teeth to make the unvoiced th,
the tongue tip absolutely has to come through the teeth.
But the voiced th can be different. When it's
in an unstressed quick word like these or the
The tongue tip doesn't have to come through the
teeth. It can press behind the teeth make sure
the tongue isn't at the roof of the mouth or
pointing down but pressing right in the middle
where the teeth come together. If it's not in the right position the sound will be wrong.
This tongue shortcut works in these words because
they're unstressed so when you don't bring your
tongue tip through the teeth it allows you to
make these less important words quickly. These,
the. Let's look at these sounds up close
and in slow motion. Notice how it's just
the very tip that comes out of the teeth.
The tongue is relaxed the teeth surround it
but they're not clamping down on it. The lips
and face are relaxed throw notice how the lips
are starting to flare for the r as the tongue
comes through the teeth for the unvoiced th.
Birthday. Keep in mind when you only stick the
very tip of your tongue out the movement into
other sounds isn't as hard as you might think.
Watch the tongue tip come in and flip up for the d.
This is a quick move of the tongue that you can
practice over and over to make it more natural.
Brother. Tongue tip through the teeth for
the voiced th lips and tongue are relaxed.
Worth. Ending in the unvoiced th. Again
the lips and tongue look very relaxed.
Remember to keep your tongue relaxed
and soft when you practice this sound.
The voiced and unvoiced th.
throw
birthday
brother
worth
Example words repeat with me.
other
either
though
Thursday
nothing
south