In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to learn how to make the W sound.
To make this sound, ww--, the
lips form a tight circle. Ww--
The back part of the tongue
stretches up towards the soft palate.
While the front part of the tongue lightly
touches the back of the bottom front teeth.
To give this sound the right quality, you have to
close the vocal cords to get this sound: ww-- ww--
Ww-- which we add to the sound ww--
You release the vocal cords as you release
the lips, coming out of the W sound. Ww--
Let's look at the sound up
close and in slow motion.
With the tight circle for the lips,
you can't see the tongue at all.
But it lifts in the back. The word 'why'.
A tight circle for the lips.
The word 'west'.
Again, a tight circle for the lips.
The word 'unwind'. Here, the W
is in the middle of the word.
We still take the time to bring
the lips into a tight circle.
This sound is most common
at the beginning of words.
It doesn't occur at the end of any
words, though the letter W does.
The W consonant.
Why
West
Unwind
Example words. Repeat with me.
Water. Ww-- Water.
Welcome. Ww-- Welcome.
Rework. Ww-- Rework.
Away. Ww-- Away.
Between. Ww-- Between.
Will. Ww-- Will.