In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to go over how
to pronounce the Y consonant.
To make the Y sound, the jaw drops a little bit.
Yy--
The lips may be relaxed, or they may begin
to take the position of the next sound.
The tongue tip is down, lightly touching
the back of the bottom front teeth.
The middle part of the tongue lifts
and touches the roof of the mouth.
It pushes forward against the roof
of the mouth before pulling away.
As we push the tongue forward
on the roof of the mouth,
we close the vocal cords to
get this sound. Yy-- yy--
which we add to the sound yyi-- yyi--
We release them the same
time we release the tongue.
Relaxed jaw drop and the lips are relaxed.
The tongue tip is down while the
middle of the tongue presses forward
against the roof of the mouth.
The word 'yes'. The tongue tip is down,
while the middle of the tongue presses
forward against the roof of the mouth.
The tongue releases into the EH as in Bed vowel.
The word 'youth'.
Notice how the lips begin
to round for the next sound.
The OO as in Boo vowel.
Yell
The tongue tip is down
while the middle of the tongue presses
forward against the roof of the mouth.
Releasing into the EH as in Bed vowel.
This sound is most common
at the beginning of words.
It doesn't occur at the end of any words
though the letter Y does.
The Y sound. Yes.
Youth
Yell
Example words. Repeat with me.
Yeah. Yy-- yeah.
Unusual. Yy-- unusual.
Senior. Yy-- senior.
You. Yy-- you.
Yesterday. Yy-- yesterday.
Yellow. Yy-- yellow.