In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to learn how to
pronounce the L consonant sound.
This sound is especially difficult.
There are actually two kinds of Ls
and they're not made the same way.
But if you look up a word in the dictionary,
there's only one International Phonetic
Alphabet symbol for both kinds of L.
In this video, you'll learn
when to make which kind of L.
First, the light L sound.
This is what most people think
of when they think of an L.
The L is a Light L when it comes before
the vowel or diphthong in a syllable.
For example, let’s— flake— release—
There are two different ways
native speakers make this sound.
One way is to lift the
tongue so the tip is touching
the roof of the mouth just behind the front teeth.
This is not the same as the
T, D, and N tongue positions
where the tongue lifts so the top
is touching the roof of the mouth.
This is the tip.
Another way native speakers make
this sound looks like the TH
with the tongue tip touching the
bottom of the top front teeth.
The contact with the teeth is
more firm than the TH sound
pushing up on the top teeth.
The tongue is not as loose or
relaxed in the L as it is in the TH.
Let's look at the Light L
up close and in slow motion.
Here's one way to make the L with the
tongue tip coming through the teeth
to press up on the bottom of the top front teeth.
Here's the second way to make the Light L.
The tip at the roof of the
mouth just behind the teeth.
Here's the word ‘lack’.
The tongue comes through the
teeth to make the light L.
The word ‘slow’,
the Light L is made with the tongue
tip at the roof of the mouth.
The second kind of L is the Dark L.
This is the sound that happens when the
L comes after the vowel or diphthong
in a word or syllable like ‘real’ or ‘Google’.
This sound has two parts but many Americans
leave out to the second part in most cases.
You should, too. It makes it easier to pronounce.
The first and most important part
of the Dark L is the dark sound.
This defines the Dark L.
To make this sound, you
don't lift your tongue tip.
Instead, it's down touching the
back of the bottom front teeth.
The back part of the tongue
pulls back towards the throat.
You can see there isn't much jaw
drop and the lips are relaxed.
Llll— you should feel the vibration
in the throat and not the face. Lll—
The back part of the tongue
presses down or shifts back.
This is an important part of the sound ull— ull—
Most Americans will stop
there when making the Dark L.
Real—
Google—
Thoughtful—
Unless they're linking into a word that begins
with an L or a sound with a similar position
like N, T, or D.
In that case, go ahead and make
the second part of the Dark L.
The second part of the Dark L is the Light L.
Bring your tongue tip up to the roof
of the mouth or through the teeth.
Some native speakers make the full
Dark L both parts all the time.
What's important is the dark sound.
Make it with the back of the tongue and
make sure you never leave that part out.
Ull— ulll—
Again, the Dark L has two parts.
The first and most important part, the tongue
pulls back or presses down in the back.
The second part, which is often left out,
either option for the Light L.
Here, the option with the tongue tip
at the roof of the mouth is pictured.
Let's look at the Dark L up
close and in slow motion.
The word ‘feel’.
The tongue tip arches in
the front for the EE vowel.
Watch as the tongue lowers in the back.
Now, the tongue is lowered, pulling
back a little bit in the back.
It's hard to see because of the lips but
the tip of the tongue is still forward.
Notice that the lips are relaxed.
The word ‘recall’. The dark part is made with
the back of the tongue as the jaw closes.
This time the Dark L does end
with the second part the Light L.
The tongue tip quickly comes through the teeth.
Lips are relaxed.
The relaxation of the lips
is important in the Dark L.
Many non-native speakers want to round or
flare the lips which brings the
sound forward and changes it.
But the dark sound is made back here.
Leave the lips relaxed so the sound
can be made in the back of the mouth.
When you look at the International Phonetic
Alphabet transcription for a word in a dictionary,
you'll just see one symbol whether
it's a Light L or a Dark L.
It's up to you to know when to make a Dark L.
when the L comes at the end of a syllable.
Remember we're talking about
sounds and not letters.
In the example, ‘Google’, you
see the letter E after the L.
E is a vowel but when you look at the
phonetic transcription of the word,
the last sound is the L.
So the L in ‘Google’ is a Dark L.
ull— ull— Google—
If you integrate a good Dark L into your
speech, it will help you sound more American.
The Light L.
Black—
Slow—
The Dark L.
Feel—
Recall—
Example words. Repeat with me.
Love. ull— Love.
Hello. ull— Hello.
Flat. ull— Flat.
Feel. ull— Feel.
Table. ull— Table.
People. ull— People.