Most advanced—even fluent—English students
have had a shocking experience when they try
to have a conversation in English: they don’t
speak with confidence.
The sounds of American English are hard.
And many people have never learned the correct
pronunciation of each specific sound.
Welcome to your Sounds of American English
course.
In this course you’ll learn exactly how
to make each sound in American English by
studying how to move your tongue, lips, and
jaw through illustrations and close-ups of
the mouth.
You’ll even learn the phonetic symbols for
each sound, which is so important with English
since it’s not a phonetic language.
Letters don’t always match with the sounds
you would expect to hear.
What?
This is ‘colonel’?
Where’s the R?!?
How comfortable are you making the TH?
What about the American R?
Don’t let your spoken English skills get
in the way of confidently meeting and speaking
with others in English.
“The limits of my language mean the limits
of my world.”
What are your limits?
Leave them behind as you build a solid foundation
for spoken English by perfecting the building
blocks – the Sounds of American English.
You can do this.