Today I'm going to go over the idiom 'on fire'.
This means to be doing something very well.
For example, you're at a basketball game,
and there's a guy who keeps hitting 3-pointer
after 3-pointer after 3-pointer, and making
them. You might say, man that guy's on fire.
It can also apply to a social situation. For
example, let's say you go to a party with
a friend. And your friend is talking to everyone,
making everyone laugh, everyone wants to be
around him. You can say, 'Man, you were on
fire at that party.' On can be pronounced
with the 'aw' as in 'law' vowel, or the 'ah'
as in 'father' vowel. I pronounce it with
the 'aw' as in 'law'. It's a little further
back in the face than the 'ah' as in 'father',
which is a little further forward. On, the
N consonant sound, so the tongue will raise
into that position. On, ff, fire begins with
the F consonant sound, so you'll raise the
bottom lip, ff, to the top teeth and let air
come through. On ff, on fi-, the 'ai' as in
'buy' diphthong, on fi-re. And finally, the
schwa and R sound, er, er. On fire, on fire.