In this American English pronunciation video,
we'll look at English in action and take a
look at the 'aa' vowel followed by nasal consonants.
>> Hey Jovon, happy Easter.
>> Oh, hey, happy Easter.
>> Hi Ben.
>> Hello Rachel.
>> Happy Easter.
>> Ben brought a ham for us to eat.
>> I brought a ham.
>> Ben brings a ham every year because he's
a dear. And I don't mean deer the animal,
I mean dear, D-E-A-R, a kind and thoughtful
person. 'Dear' and 'deer' are homophones.
>> What is this, Ben?
>> This is a ham. And it is made with pineapple
and brown sugar.
>> Oh, delicious. Ham. This is a teachable moment.
>> Here comes the ham. Now the word ham --
>> (it's really hot)
>> -- is an interesting word because it's
the AA as in BAT vowel followed by a nasal
consonant, in this case, M. So even though
it's written in IPA just with the H consonant,
AA vowel, and M consonant, it's not actually
pronounced that way. That would be "haam",
"haam". But we say, ha-uh-m. And there's that
UH sound that's not accounted for in IPA:
aa-uh, aa-uh. Ham. So, if you add this UH
sound to your AA vowel, you'll sound much
more American. Other examples, camera. AA-UH-M.
Cam-, Camera. This is also true if the sound
after the AA is the N sound. For example,
'ant'. AA-UHnt. Ant. Now, one last thing.
If the AA vowel is followed by the NG consonant,
then it changes also, but, in a different
way. In that case it becomes a sound more
like the 'ay' diphthong, ay. For example,
in the word 'thanks': thanks. Or, bank, bank.
So pronounce your AA vowel this way when it's
followed by N, M, or NG.
>> Michelle, what are you working on here?
>> I'm making Eggs Benedict.
>> Ooo.
>> So I'm poaching eggs --
>> Uh-huh.
>> And then making them with salmon and spinach.
>> Oh, that looks delicious.
>> Jovon's always taking pictures. It's a
good thing I'm used to the camera, right?
So this is what I made for our meal. Some
green---it probably doesn't look as good under
plastic, eh? Some asparagus. I roasted it
yesterday, gonna serve it chilled with a dijon
vinaigrette. Yum.
>> What did you make, Kate?
>> I made Easter egg chocolate / peanut butter
candy.
>> Oo, that looks good. Now these are special,
right?
>> They're special: they're vegan.
>> They're vegan.
>> No dairy.
>> Wow. Let me zoom up on that. Jovon's been
trying to sneak one of those ever since you
made them yesterday.
>> I found the little ladle. That's a hard
little phrase. Say that five times quickly!
Little ladle [x5].
>> Ben, this ham is delicious.
>> Thanks.
>> You guys are so clear, such good actors
for my Rachel's English audience. Totally
natural.
>> They're hamming it up.
>> They are hamming it up. Thank you, Matthew,
for brining up another use of the word 'ham'.
Matthew cleverly pointed out a second definition
for the word 'ham'. An actor or performer
who overacts. As a verb: to act with exaggerated
expression of emotion, to overact. So the
idiom, to ham it up, simply means, to overact.
Example sentence: He really hammed it up for
the camera.
>> Happy Easter, guys.
>> Happy Easter, Rachel.
>> Hope you're learning lots of fun vocabulary.
>> They are.
>> We learned all about the word 'ham'.
>> Ham.
>> Oo, ham.
>> That's a good one.
>> It is a good one and --
>> It's a nasal one.
>> -- it's sort of an odd word because it's
got this AA-UH sound.
>> haa, haaa. Like that.
>> Yeah. If you had to explain how you pronounce
'ham', what would you say?
>> Um, haa, aa. There's an H in there.
>> Yes?
>> There's an A, with an aa, kind of an aa?
>> Very nasal aa sound.
>> M, and then an M, mm, mm.
>> So if you had to say it in slow motion,
say it in slow motion.
>> Haaauhm.
>> There you go! I heard that good UH sound.
HaQuyen?
>> Ham.
Let's watch this in slow motion. As you know,
AA followed by M has an 'uh' sound. AA-uh,
AA-uh. You can see HaQuyen's tongue pull back
to make that UH sound before her lips close
for the M.
>> Ham.
>> Yeah, nice
>> Got that in the profile.
>> Yep, she gave the profile so we can see
the movement of the tongue and everything.
Thanks guys!
>> You're welcome Rachel.
>> You're most welcome.
That's it, and thanks so much
for using Rachel's English.
Don't stop there. Have fun with my real-life
English videos. Or get more comfortable with
the IPA in this play list. Learn about the
online courses I offer, or check out my latest
video.