Today I'm going to go over the idiom 'out
like a light'. I can mean two different things.
It can mean in a very deep sleep, or it can
mean unconscious. I actually found myself
using this the other day describing how well
I was sleeping. I didn't hear the sirens last
night, I was out like a light. However, I've
also used it before for having been unconscious.
I was chopping vegetables one day not too
long ago and I cut off the very end of my
thumb. And I ended up at the ER. And when
they took the bandage off of my thumb, I immediately
passed out. I was out like a light. This phrase
begins with the 'ow' as in 'now' diphthong,
ow, ow, and it then has the T. It's a final
T, so you might hear it as a stop T, out,
out, or you might hear it lightly released,
out, out. Like, the L consonant sound and
the 'ai' as in 'buy' diphthong. Out li-, out
li-, kk. The K consonant sound -- out like,
out like, a. The schwa. Out like a. Out like
a. And finally, light, the L consonant sound,
the 'ai' as in 'buy' diphthong, and again
a final T. So, it might be stopped, or it
might be released. Light or light. You'll
notice the words 'out' and 'light' are the
stressed words here. Out like a light. Out
like a light. I was out like a light.