Today we’re going to go
over the pronunciation
for the idiom ‘to pay
through the nose’.
You might use this phrase when
you are talking about something
that you’ve paid a large
amount of money for.
For example, someone might say, I
love your car and you might say,
Yes, I paid through the nose for it.
Or, for example, I paid through
the nose for my computer
and it broke in the first week.
Another example: I’d like
to live in Manhattan,
but you have to pay through
the nose to live there.
Pay begins with the unvoiced
pp P consonant sound
and is followed by the ‘ay’
as in ‘say’ diphthong.
Pay.
Through.
The TH here is unvoiced
th, th, through.
The R sound is followed by the
‘oo’ as in ‘boo’ vowel sound.
Pay through.
The.
Here, the TH is voiced, and the schwa
sound makes up the rest of the word.
Nose begins with the
N consonant sound,
followed by the ‘oh’ as in
‘no’ diphthong, no-, no-,
and finally, zz, the
voiced Z consonant sound.
Nose.
Pay through the nose.
The two stressed words in
this phrase are pay,
or paid if you are speaking
in the past tense, and nose.
You have to pay through the nose.