In this American English Pronunciation video,
we're going to go over the idiom 'in the loop.'
Have you ever heard anyone say "keep me in
the loop", or, "I want to stay in the loop"?
This idiom means to be informed or connected.
For example, if you're working on a project
at work, and you've just been talking about
it. To let your coworkers know that you're
interested in staying involved or informed,
you can say, "Great, keep me in the loop."
So, keep me in the loop, or stay in the loop:
it's the verb and the word 'loop', a noun,
that are stressed. The unstressed words
will be less loud, very quick, and lower in
pitch: in the, in the, in the. A tip to
get these two function words connected is
to sort of make the N and TH at the same time.
My tongue tip can be just peeking out of the
teeth for the TH while this part of the tongue,
the front part, is actually up touching here,
where the N is made. So I don't have to
move my tongue between those two sounds.
That will help me say these two function words
very quickly. You may notice there's not
really a strong TH sound, in the, in the.
Don't worry about that, just make sure your
tongue tip is between the teeth. The tongue
pulls back to make the quick schwa sound in
'the', in the, in the, and then the tip of
the tongue goes back to the roof of the mouth
for the Light L of 'loop'. In the lll-.
It's the tip that's up at the roof of the
mouth, so the tongue will bend this way, ll.
The OO as in BOO vowel is next, so you must
round your lips, and finally the P consonant
where the lips come together and part, releasing
a light burst of air. Loop, since it's stressed,
it will have the up-down curve in the voice,
loop, and be longer than 'in the'. In the
loop, in the loop. Keep me in the loop.
Practice your English: make up a phrase
with the idiom "In the Loop" and record yourself.
Post it as a video response to this video
on YouTube. I can't wait to watch!
That's it, and thanks so much for using
Rachel's English.