In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to go over the idiom 'hit the
bullseye'.
>> Let me try one more time.
>> You aren't actually trying. Please tell
me...
>> Hold on, hold on.
>> Triple 7. Double 7. Double 7.
>> Folks, that's how it's done.
In the mean time, let me just quickly tell
the users out there how to pronounce 'bullseye'.
Because that it what this video is about.
It's a two-syllable phrase with stress on
the first syllable. DA-da. Bullseye. So we
begin with the B consonant sound, lips are
together. Then we have the UH as in PULL vowel,
but because it's followed by a Dark L, it's
really just a dark sound. Bull-, uhl. So I'm
pulling the back part of the tongue back, while
the tip of the tongue stays forward. Bulls-.
Now, I don't bring my tongue tip up. I just
go straight into the Z. So my teeth close,
my tongue tip stays where it is, bullseye.
Then I have the AI as in BUY diphthong. Jaw
does need to drop for the first half of that
diphthong. Ai, ii, and then my jaw drops less
as the tongue lifts up towards the roof of
the mouth for the second half of the diphthong.
Bullseye, DA-da. Make sure you get the rhythm
in there. The rhythm is really important.
We want long, then short. DA-da. Bullseye.
To hit the bullseye literally means to hit
the center of a target, something I'm clearly
not able to do. Figuratively, it means to
do something just right, to get the best result
possible, to be exactly right. Hit the bullseye.
Notice we have a Stop T in the word 'hit'.
That's because the next word begins with a
consonant. Also, notice how it's stressed.
It's louder, higher in pitch than the next
word, the, which is unstressed. Hit the. Hit
the. You can simplify things here by making
a Stop T. First, make the H consonant and
the IH as in SIT vowel. Hi-, hi-. Then, put
your tongue into position for the TH, with
the tip coming just through the teeth. As you
do this, stop the air quickly in the throat
to make the stop. Then, you're already in
the right position for the TH. Hit the [3x].
Hit the bullseye.
To hit the bullseye, is also like to hit the
nail on the head, another idiom, which basically
means, that's exactly right. So, for example,
I might say, 'I'm not feeling well, I'm not
really sure...' And a friend who knows me
may say, 'You know what, you're not happy
at work.' And I'm thinking, 'You know what?
That's right.' And I say, 'You hit the bullseye.
You hit the nail on the head.' Now, I'm going
to try to hit a bullseye. So, cheer me on.
Let's hear it.
>> Rachel, Rachel.
>> This is a difficult game.
>> Yeah.
>> Probably, the chances are, at least one
of my fans is a dart expert.
>> Amen.
>> So, I'm going to say, please put in the
comments below any tips you have. Anything
you see about my form that should be corrected.
>> That's smart.
>> Tom, what did the dart board just say?
>> It said, 'Remove darts'.
>> So, dart. Can you hold up the dart? This
is a dart as a noun. But it's also a verb.
>> That's true.
The verb 'to dart' means to move quickly.
A mouse might dart across the floor, or your
eyes might dart in the direction of a sudden
sound. This word has the AH + R combination,
which can be a challenge for some speakers.
You want to make sure that you drop your jaw
with the tongue forward: da-, dar-, before
you pull your tongue back for the R, so you
can get a good vowel sound. Dart, dart. Remember,
if you want to link the word 'dart' into a
word that begins with a vowel, make the T
a flap T. For example, dart around. Dart a-,
dart a-, dart around.
>> That's it, and thanks so much for using
Rachel's English.