In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to go over the idiom 'landslide'.
This idiom is in honor of March Madness, which
will start soon. March Madness is a college
basketball tournament that happens every year
about this time. A very exciting couple of
weeks for sports fans! A landslide victory,
or, to win in a landslide, is a victory by
a large margin. In basketball, maybe something
like 20 points. You could also use this term
to describe an election. He was elected Mayor
in a landslide.
Landslide. Do you notice that I'm dropping
the D? When the D comes after an N and before
another consonant, you can drop the D. Landslide.
Another example would be 'grandma'. No D sound
there. Grandma.
This is a two-syllable word with stress on
the first syllable. Landslide. It begins with
the Light L, ll, tongue tip here. Ll, ll,
la-. Then the AA as in BAT vowel. Make sure
you drop your jaw for that. Laa, aa. Also
the top lip may pull up a bit. La-, la-. Next
is the nasal consonant N. And you may know
that AA followed by a nasal consonant isn't
really a pure AA. We have an 'uh' sound in
there, where the tongue relaxes in the back.
La-uh-, la-uh-n. Before the front raises for
the N sound. Lan, nn, nn. So it's the front,
flat part of the tongue that is touching the
roof of the mouth there for the N. Lan, landsss-,
then the S consonant sound. The teeth come
together, ss, and the tongue then goes to
the roof of the mouth for the L. For the N
it was touching like this, and for the L it
touches like this, with the very tip. Then
the AI as in BUY diphthong. Again, drop your
jaw for the first sound of the diphthong.
-sli-. And finally, a light D at the end,
where the flat part of the tongue will quickly
touch the roof of the mouth. Landslide, landslide,
landslide.
Practice your English. Make up a sentence
using 'landslide', record it, and post it
as a video response on YouTube to this video.
I can't wait to see it.
That's it, and thanks so much
for using Rachel's English.