In this American English pronunciation video,
we're going to ride our bikes into Brooklyn
to make some pizza. And of course, you'll
learn some American English pronunciation
on the way, including the idioms to catch
up and to fill in. Oh boy!
This is my bicycle, Jenny. I didn't name her,
she came named. Tonight we're going to go
for a bike ride into Brooklyn. Brooklyn is
the borough just east of Manhattan (one of
the boroughs just east of Manhattan). So let's
look at Brooklyn. It has two O's. Now, there
are four different ways to pronounce two O's:
oo, as in boo, uh as in book, uh as in blood,
and oh as in brooch. So how is it pronounced
in Brooklyn? Uh, uh, Brooklyn. What's your
guess? The answer is: it's the same as the
vowel in 'book'. Brooklyn. Now. Let's get
going before it gets dark.
It's about a 45-minute bike ride from my home
in Manhattan to my friend's home in Brooklyn.
It involves taking the Manhattan bridge over
the East River.
>> Hey.
It's seven o'clock on the nose, seven o'clock
sharp. Those idioms mean, of course, exactly
seven o'clock. We're right on time. We're very
punctual. Punk - chew - ul. Let's go Sara.
>> So we rode our bikes in from Brooklyn.
>> No! In from Manhattan!
>> We rode our bikes from Manhattan into Brooklyn
--- because it's been a while since we've
seen each other. So we're making some dinner,
we're making pizza, and we're going to catch up.
>> We're going to catch up. [2x]
>> Find out what's going on in each other's lives.
>> That's right. Catch up. An idiom that you
would use if you haven't seen somebody in
a while, and you want to know what's going
on. You would say, "let's catch up". You could
also say, "fill me in". What else could you
say? Ketchup, by the way, spelled this way,
is also a condiment.
>> This girl can cook. You remember -- from
the turkey.
Cook. Does that 'uh' sound sound familiar?
It's the same sound as in 'book' and 'Brooklyn'.
Listen again.
>> This girl can cook. You remember -- from
the turkey.
>> Oh boy.
>> Oh boy. I like that phrase.
>> Oh boy?
>> It's a good one. What, do you say that
when you're exasperated? Oh boy.
>> Overwhelmed, like when you're overwhelmed?
>> It's a good one. Oh boy.
>> Or excited.
>> Or excited. Oh boy!
>> Is this done Beads? I don't know?
>> Yeah, no, I mean, yeah, I think, well.
The first pie always takes longer because
of the oven.
Did you hear how I said 'cuz of the oven'?
Cuzof, cuzof, cuzof. If I said that out of
the context of a sentence, nobody would know
what I was talking about. But as a part of
the whole, that's they way it makes sense
to say it. Cuzof. We reduce it, it's low in
pitch, cuzofthe, cuzofthe, cuzofthe oven.
Then the 'oven' is the stressed word. So,
this is very important in English: that the
function words, the less important words,
are low in pitch, strung together, maybe reduced,
to contrast with the shape of the stressed
word: cuzofthe oven.
>> So, when it's pretty much cooked. Actually,
when it's cooked.
>> Hold on, did you, did you guys notice,
she just said 'pretty', with a flap T. Can
you say that again?
>> What? It's pretty much?
>> Yeah, but say it at the camera!
>> Pretty much.
>> Thank you for the demonstration.
>> You're welcome!
>> Ok, when it's pretty much cooked?
>> When it's pretty much cooked, we're going
to bring it out, and we're going to put arugula---
>> Hold on. Did you notice? She's using 'gonna'.
We're gonna bring it out, we're gonna put
arugula.
>> Yes, we're going to put arugula, and we're
going to put prosciutto, and we're going to
crumble some more blue cheese and we're going
to drizzle it with honey.
>> Wow, that sounds amazing, and it was such
a good demonstration of using 'gonna'. Thank
you.
>> You're welcome.
>> This looks pretty good. Pretty good.
>> Pretty: flap T!
>> Ok. Let's slice this baby up.
>> My favorite topping: pepperoni. I like
it almost as much as I like buying shoes.
Then we made a second pizza, totally different
from the first, and sat down to a nice meal.
After the lovely evening, it was time to say
good-bye.
>> Bye! Thank you so much!
>> Bye! You're welcome.
>> It was good to see you, it was so good
to catch up!
>> It was good to catch up.
That's it, and thanks so much
for using Rachel's English.
Don't stop there. Have fun with my real-life
English videos. Or get more comfortable with
the IPA in this play list. Learn about the
online courses I offer, or check out my latest
video.