Have you ever wondered how to say the word
'chili'? In this American English pronunciation
video, you'll learn how to. I took my video
camera with me to two different Super Bowl parties.
>> You're going there first?
>> I'm going to Mark and Hillary's first.
I'm, I'm kind of going before, probably before--
>> I thought you were--
>> You thought what?
>> I thought you were coming after.
>> Well, I kind of decided that I might not
even--
Here I reduced 'kind of' to 'kinda'. I admit,
I'm talking really fast here. I wasn't actually
planning on using this footage. But it is
true that sometimes people do speak that quickly.
'Kind of' reduced to 'kinda'. Listen again.
>> Well, I kind of decided that I might not
even-- [x3]
even stay through the end of the game.
>> Oh.
>> I just feel like I have a lot to do tomorrow
because I have a lot to get ready for.
>> Are you bringing anything?
>> Yeah, but I have to go to the store first.
I don't know what I'm going to bring. Do you
have any suggestions?
>> Um, no.
This is my friend Hillary, and yes, she's
a little crazy.
>> Hey, go Giants! AHHH!
>> This is my friend Mark, who's hosting a
Super Bowl party. Mark, who do you think's
going to win tonight?
>> I think the Patriots are going to win.
>> Why?
>> What?!?
>> I think the Patriots are going to win because
their offense is better than the Giants' defense.
And, they've got Tom Brady and Super Bowl
experience.
>> How do you feel about saying that while
you are in the state of New York?
>> I'm from Philadelphia. So, I don't like
the Giants to start with, and I don't like
the Patriots either. So, I can be very objective.
>> You just wanted a reason to throw a good party.
>> Exactly.
>> It works.
>> Hillary, who do you think's going to win?
>> I'm going Giants all the way. Um, I feel
like Eli Manning really brings it, um, he
brings it to the table.
>> Uh-huh.
Hillary used the idiom 'to bring something
to the table'. This means to provide a useful
skill. For example, I'm partnering with Tom
in my business because he's great at marketing.
He really brings something to the table. She
used a generic bring it to the table, meaning
'it', that something special, in this case,
that makes one win football games. Listen again.
>> He brings it to the table. [x3]
>> He brings it to the table.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Um, I also think since we're in New York,
it's just more fun to root for the Giants.
>> I think you're right.
>> So, that's my take.
>> And, can you tell me what you guys have
got going here? Now, I'm here early, I'm here
before all of the other guests. But I hear
that there's chili to be had.
>> There's tons of chili, vegetarian and meat.
>> Can you step through how to pronounce 'chili',
Hillary?
Did you notice? I reduced the word 'can'.
That's because it's a helping verb here, the
main verb being 'step through'. Can you step
through. Kn, kn, can you step through. Listen
again.
>> Can you step through how to pronounce 'chili',
Hillary?
>> Uh, I would say 'chili'.
>> But how do you do it? What do you do to
your mouth?
>> Well you, you go-- chuh, like, chuh-li--
>> Ok you know what guys? Forget her. I will
teach you how to say 'chili'.
>> So, chili. It's a two syllable word, first
syllable is stressed. Chi-li. It begins with
the CH consonant sound, ch, ch, opening into
the 'ih' as in 'sit' vowel, chi-. Then, there's
a dark L, so the tongue will pull back a little
bit, chil-, before finishing with the tongue
in the top position. Chil-i. Finally, the
unaccented syllable is the 'ee' as in 'she'
vowel. In both syllables, the vowel sound
is written with the I, but in the first syllable,
it represents the IH sound, and in the second
syllable, the EE sound.
>> Chili. The first syllable tastes delicious.
The second syllable tastes delicious.
>> Isn't it really hot?
>> Chili, yum.
>> Mark, can I help you with anything?
>> No, I think I'm good. Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
Did you notice? Mark used the phrase 'I'm
good'. You can use this to decline an offer.
Would you like a glass of water? I'm good.
Can I get you anything else? I'm good. Can
I help you with anything? No, I think I'm
good. Listen again.
>> No, I think I'm good. Thank you. [x3]
>> No, I think I'm good. Thank you.
Now on to the next party for more chili
and to watch the game.
>> Look! It's Eli Manning! I thought he was
going to be in Indianapolis at the game!
>> It's just me Dan.
>> Thanks for watching my Super Bowl video.
Did you watch the Super Bowl? Leave a comment
if you did.
That's it, and thanks so much for using Rachel's
English.